Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
- Record Group 17. (RESTRICTED) Digital formats (1989-2013, undated; 4.5 linear feet), 1989-2016, undated; 4.5 Linear feet
  - Various - CD, 1998-2016 (Offsite-box 291)
    ECF Annual Report 1998-1999, ECF photos 2002, ECFS PDF 2002, Ethical Culture final upgrade Millennium 2004, Fieldston draft S!P 2005, Field Notes campus construction 2006, Field Notes 2007, Fieldston Athletics from 1904 to Present 2007, April projects 2007, Photos from big screen 2008-2009, FLS classrooms 2016.
  - Various - CD, undated (Offsite-box 291)
    0130007, 125 Video, AV, Black and whites, Board finals, BW,S Dec Asst, Crescent, EC roof/science/art, ECS 125 Video, ECFS calendar possibilities, ECF directory, ES DataBank, Fashion Quad, Fieldston - final, Fieldston Lower art, Fieldston School - draft, First grade photoshow (Mac version), Flags/Ethical, Founder's Day, Founders rough position only, Ginger BD selects, Harlem Lanes, Head shots, Green carnival, I am, "I am time" - Cubano jazz, Kate selects (3), May 10 master, May uncredited, Missing persons (2), Mousetrap race, MUSLCTS (3), MUZ.112, Nina dinner (2), Nina backup, NF, Oct 15/music room, Parents INT 1, PEPL 20, Photos for website, Pool pix, Senior project, Science selects, Steven Lubin piano, Terry recept, To Toby Himmel "for the archives" (2). Two missing ports, Visual arts - for 16x20 prints.
  - Supplementary materials, 1990-2008 (Offsite-box 287)
    Fieldston Lower Songs - 3 copies of CDs and booklets with lyrics, 1998. Various, 2007-2008. Various Fieldston Lower, 2008. Snoopy, 2008. Spring Film Festival, 2012. Ephemera and notes, 2002-2008, undated. Guide to Dr. Melvin Levine audiotapes, 1990.
  - 3.5 inch floppy disks - New York Association of Independent Schools, 1992, undated (Offsite-box 293)
    8 discs relating to the NYAIS evaluation, with materials including departmental information, and parent and Board of Governors surveys.
  - 3.5 inch floppy disks - Various, 1989-2001 (Offsite-box 293)
    Brochure, 1989. Afterschool logo/Day Camp, 1990. Voices of the Computer Room, 1990. Fieldston Summer Science Academy brochure/Director's Newsletter, 1990. Faculty Handbook, 1990. Various, 1991. FSSA brochures, 1990-1992. FAC grants, 1992. Grid Fall, 1992. Various, 1998-1999. Annual Report/Campaign Report, 1998-1999. ECFS/labels for Annual Report, 1999. Reply card, 1999. Founder's Day speeches/Judy Birnkrant, 1999. ECS Reporter, 2000. Class notes for ECS Reporter (2), 2001.
  - 3.5 inch floppy disks - Various, undated (Offsite-box 293)
    11 discs containing various undated documents.
  - 3.5 inch floppy disks - "Janice's files", undated (Offsite-box 293)
    12 discs, with varying labels including "J.A. files" and numbered discs. Two discs also labeled Benefits.
  - 3.5 inch floppy disks - Seven unlabeled discs, undated (Offsite-box 293)
  - 5.25 inch floppy disks, undated (Offsite-box 326)
    Six boxes containing approximately 10 disks each, labled either "Reader" or "Ethical Culture."
  - Zip 100 disks, 2000, undated (Offsite-box 293)
    Five discs, four labeled Edward Smith Design, with one also labeled ECS Reporter Vol. 48. One unlabeled.
  - Digital Audio Tape (DAT) - Various, 2001-2007 (Offsite-box 293)
    Sixth grade recital, 2001. Holiday Assembly (8), 2001-2007. Norse myths (3), 2002-2003. Fourth grade biographies (8), 2002-2006. Fieldston Lower graduation (7), 2002-2007. Thanksgiving Assembly (6), 2002-2007. Harvest Festival (5), 2003-2007. World Music Assembly (6), 2003-2007. Evening concert (2), 2005-2006. MLK Assembly (4), 2004-2007. IF Bird Museum, 2005. Fourth grade recital, 2007. Fifth and Sixth grade concert, 2007. Wolf Assembly, 2007.
  - Digital Audio Tape (DAT) - Music and jazz departments, 1998-2005 (Offsite-box 293)
    Spring concert, 1998. Fieldston studio work, 2000. Jazz concert, 2004. Holiday concert, 2004. Chamber, 2005. Middle School spring concert, 2005 (2). Jazz concert, 2005. Evening of song, 2005. Spring orchestra, 2005 (2). Colleen kids, undated. Session tape, undated. Unlabeled and undated tape.
  - Digital Audio Tape (DAT) - Jazz programs, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 293)
    Vocal jazz, 2002. Jazz concert, 2005 (2). Also one unlabeled tape.
  - Mini DV - Assemblies, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 293)
    World Music Assembly, 2003 (2) and 2004. Harvest Festival, 2003 and 2004. MLK Assembly, 2004, 2005, and 2006. Holiday Assembly, 2001 (2), 2003 (2), 2004, and 2005. Thanksgiving Assembly, 2002, 2003, 2004, and 2005.
  - Mini DV - Lower schools, 2002-2006 (Offsite-box 293)
    Fieldston Lower graduation, 2002 (2), 2003 (2), 2004 (2). Grade six graduation, 2004 (2). Fourth grade biographies, 2002 (2), 2004 (2). Norse myths, 2002, 2003. Sixth grade recital, 2001. Evening concert, 2005, 2006. 1F Bird Museum, 2005.
- Record Group 18. (RESTRICTED) Student records (circa 1910-1940; 70 linear feet), 74 Linear feet
  Some student records from the early decades of the twentieth century are held in the collection, dating through about 1940. These include student files from the midtown school and the Fieldston campus. This record group does not include student records from the Normal School (last graduating class was in 1941), which are found in Record Group 2. These student records are all closed to general access until 2040. New-York Historical Society generally holds no student records for graduating classes from 1940 and later, though a very few random files from the early 1940s appear to have been interfiled with the earlier files. The files include grades, qualitative evaluations, permission slips, correspondence, notes on college acceptances, etc. The files include some documents from years after the student left ECFS such as requests for transcripts, clippings (regarding marriages and the like), and other individual alumni matters.
  There are three sets of records: files for graduating classes up to 1936, files for graduating classes of 1937-1939, and index cards of records for students. Each set of files are in alphabetical order by student surname. The index cards were originally labeled as "withdrawn students through 1936," but there are cards for students through 1940 (and a very few from the early 1940s) and there are cards for students who graduated from tthe schools.
  The index card files are clearly incomplete as seen by the obvious gaps in the alphabetical sequence. It is not known how complete the other two sets of files are.
  To request permission to access any student historical records, contact Ethical Culture Fieldston School's Chief Operating Officer (COO). No access will be permitted without the explicit, written permission of the COO.
  The record group is arranged such that the three sets of files (to 1936, 1937 to about 1940, and index cards) are boxed in their original order as found. The files are unprocessed and remain in their original folders, which are fragile, as are some of the documents in the files.
  The index cards were rehoused from their original deteriorated boxes, but the original labels were retained, principally to help highlight the gaps in the records. The number of cards per student ranges widely, from a single card to perhaps dozens. Many, though not all, of these multiple card sets were originally held together by rubber bands, which have all dried out and crumbled apart. Consequently, care needs to be taken in using the cards to ensure that they do not get mixed up. However, many of the cards were already found mixed up during re-boxing in 2019; the archivist attempted to ensure that the order of names in the boxes were generally correct, but users should not expect the cards to be in perfect sequence within a particular student's cards or across student cards. This will be especially so for students with identical names, students with cards that referred to them by different names (e.g., Robert and Bob), and cards with variant surname spellings for the same student (e.g., Cohen/Cohn/Cone).
  The record group is closed to general access until 2040. To request permission to access any student historical records, contact Ethical Culture Fieldston School's Chief Operating Officer (COO). No access will be permitted to anyone before 2040 without the explicit, written permission of Fieldston's COO.
  - Student record files: A - Bat, To 1936 (Offsite-box 350)
  - Student record files: Bau - Bic, To 1936 (Offsite-box 351)
  - Student record files: Bie - Bra, To 1936 (Offsite-box 352)
  - Student record files: Bre - Ch, To 1936 (Offsite-box 353)
  - Student record files: Ci - Dep, To 1936 (Offsite-box 354)
  - Student record files: Des - Em, To 1936 (Offsite-box 355)
  - Student record files: En - Fo, To 1936 (Offsite-box 356)
  - Student record files: Fr - Gilb, To 1936 (Offsite-box 357)
  - Student record files: Gill - Go, To 1936 (Offsite-box 358)
  - Student record files: Gr - Ham, To 1936 (Offsite-box 359)
  - Student record files: Han - Hes, To 1936 (Offsite-box 360)
  - Student record files: Heu - Jab, To 1936 (Offsite-box 361)
  - Student record files: Jac - Ka, To 1936 (Offsite-box 362)
  - Student record files: Ke - Ku, To 1936 (Offsite-box 363)
  - Student record files: La - Lev, To 1936 (Offsite-box 364)
  - Student record files: Lew - Mal, To 1936 (Offsite-box 365)
  - Student record files: Mam - Men, To 1936 (Offsite-box 366)
  - Student record files: Mer - My, To 1936 (Offsite-box 367)
  - Student record files: Na - On, To 1936 (Offsite-box 368)
  - Student record files: Op - Pol, To 1936 (Offsite-box 369)
  - Student record files: Pom - Ri, To 1936 (Offsite-box 370)
  - Student record files: Ro, To 1936 (Offsite-box 371)
  - Student record files: Ru - Sche, To 1936 (Offsite-box 372)
  - Student record files: Schi - Sie, To 1936 (Offsite-box 373)
  - Student record files: Sil - Sp, To 1936 (Offsite-box 374)
  - Student record files: Sr - Stra, To 1936 (Offsite-box 375)
  - Student record files: Stri - Va, To 1936 (Offsite-box 376)
  - Student record files: Ve - Wel, To 1936 (Offsite-box 377)
  - Student record files: Wer - Wolff, To 1936 (Offsite-box 378)
  - Student record files: Wolfs - Z, To 1936 (Offsite-box 379)
  - Student record files: A - De, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 380)
  - Student record files: Di - Goldsm, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 381)
  - Student record files: Goldst - Je, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 382)
  - Student record files: Jo - Lie, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 383)
  - Student record files: Lin - P, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 384)
  - Student record files: R - Sh, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 385)
  - Student record files: Si - Wi, 1937-1940 (Offsite-box 386)
  - Student record files: Various, To 1940 (Offsite-box 387)
    This box includes student files found after the above boxes were packed at N-YHS. They were found together and it is not clear why they had not been filed alphabetically by ECFS with the other records. Names (class/course completion/departure year) in this box are: John (Jack) Adler (1939), Virginia Boyle (1936), Vivian Brecher (1934), Anna Chess (1929), Myron Coler (1930), Naomi Diamant (1925), Frances Field (1933), Estelle Frankfurter (1913), Janice Hubshman (1938), Stanley Kallman (1939), Gordon Kerby (1934), Angela Kitzinger (1921), Marjory Leve (1914), Evelyn Levy (1925), John Lewis (1927), Richard Machol (1929), Margaret Mather (1929), David Mintz (1939), Joyce Morganstern (1939), Judith Morganstern (1939), William Salant (1933), George Sanders (1930), Marjorie Schecter (1934), Robert Simon (1915), Robert Simons (1928), Richard Sprayregen (1939), Mirian Spectorsky (1921), Richard George Stein (1932), Elizabeth Stern (1929), Claire Weinstein/Winston (1938), Susan Wimpfheimer (1932), Arthur Winogrand (1937), Sybil Winsten (1939), Charles Wolfe (1937), Eleanor Wolfe (1937), Robert Wolff (1938), Jean Woolf (1939), Flora Wovschin (1939), Barbara Wright (1938), Jane Wright (1938), Lester Wyner (1939), Cynthia Zimmerman (1939).
  - Specifically identified student files, To 1940 (Offsite-box 379)
    While the archive was still at Fieldston, staff apparently identified the files of particular students to pull from the general run of student records to hold separately. At N-YHS these files were not re-integrated into the alpha files, but kept together as found during processing. Those separated files are in this box 379. The student names (class year) are: Louis Aborn (1930), Mischa (sp?) Auer (1926), Algernon Black (1919), Aline Bernstein (1931), Ernst Boas (1907), Abram Chasins (1921), Stella Chess (1931), Ambrose Doskow (1925), David Doskow (1927), Henry Dreyfuss (1922), Herman Jersawit/Jervis (1926), Babette Deutsch, mother of Adam Yarmolinsky (1913), Evelyn Kronman (1922), Ruth Kronman (entered 1918), Clarence Miller (1929), Howard Nemerov (1937), Dorothy Neumann (1931), Robert Oppenheimer (1921), Ithiel Pool (1935), Muriel Rukeyser (1930), Rachel Salisbury (1912), Rebecca Salisbury (1911), Adam Yarmolinsky (1939), Diane Nemerov/Arbus (1940).
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): A - BL, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 388)
    Holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Abenheimer-Banks," "Barbe-Beck," "Becker-Berliss," "Berman-Bishop," and "Black-Blumgart."
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Bo - D, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 389)
    Holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Boas-Branower," "Buchbinder-Chambers," "Chapin-Covington," a box with missing label that spanned Cr-Din (Craft-Dinkelstein), and "Dix-Elliott." (This record carton only holds up to Du; letter E is in the next carton.
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Ea - Goldw, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 390)
    Holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Dix-Elliott" (only letter E is here; letter D is in previous carton), "Ellsberg-Eyster," "Fabray-Fish," "Fisher-Friedman," and "Golde-Goldworm." There is clearly a gap, and likely missing boxes, between the box ending in Fr and that beginning with Golde. (Single stray cards for a Gilbert and for a Grossman and a set of cards for a Goldberg, and were also added to the carton's contents.)
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Ha - Ki, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 391)
    This carton holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Heller-Heymann" (some stray cards with "Ha" names found by the archivist in 2019 were added here), "Higier-House," "Howe-Jackson," "Jacob-Joy," "Kahn-Karp," and "Kimmelmann-Kopetsky" (only through Ki/Kitzinger in this carton, rest is in next carton). A few surnames begining with Kh were found out of place in another box and were added here. In addition to likely gaps in the letter K, there appears to be a sizable gap and likely missing original boxes between the "Golde-Goldw" contents ending the prior carton and the "Heller-Heymann" contents beginning this carton.
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): KL - Mer, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 392)
    Holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Kimmelmann-Kopetsky" (Ki portion is in previous carton), "Koplik-Kutner," "Lachmann-Lazare," "Levine-Lewis" (also had cards for a Liebowitz), "Loewenthal-Mc Kenzie" (does not include Ma), "Marion-Mayer," and "Mayer-Mergentine."
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Metz - Ran, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 393)
    Holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Metzger-Mix," "Moch-Mulford," "Muravchick-Nerensberg," "Nevelson-Ogden," "Onoshko-Payne," "Pearson-Poliakoff," and "Poll-Ransohoff."
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Rie - Shro, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 394)
    Holds four archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Rocker-Romanoffski" (but the box actually held names beginning Rie), "Rose-Rosenwassen," "Rosenzweig-Rubin,"Samuels, G.-Scherer," "Scheuer-Schwarz," and "Schweitzer-Shropshire."
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Si - Str, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 395)
    Holds three archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Sichel-Singher" (actually goes to Sis), "Sitten-Solomon,"Solow-Steiniger," and "Stephan-Strand" (has one card at end for Strasser). There were no cards in the boxes received by N-YHS for names beginning in T, U, V. There is also a fourth, empty archival box available to be used for any additional cards found in the future.
  - Student card file ("Withdrawn students"): Wag - Zu, To circa 1940 (Offsite-box 396)
    Holds three archival boxes of index cards. The labels on the original boxes were: "Wagner-Weis" (a couple cards for a random V (Verito) were found and placed here), "Weisberg-Winfield," "Winship-Wolfson," and "Woodward-Zubow." There is also a fourth, empty archival box available to be used for any additional cards found in the future.